[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[Road Home]
[귀로 : 너에게 돌아가는 길]
[Episode 3]
[제3화]
Lazybones.
게으름뱅이
Get up. Hurry.
일어나, 빨리
I need to get some more sleep.
좀 더 잘래
Captain Lu's men are here.
루 대장의 사람이 왔어
I haven't changed my clothes yet.
나 아직 옷 안 갈아입었는데
Look how nervous you are.
긴장하는 것 좀 봐
They're outside.
문 밖에 있어
Isn't the flight tomorrow?
내일 비행기 아니었나?
I just
어제
called him yesterday.
그에게 전화했었는데
Hello, Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모, 안녕하세요
Are you here alone?
혼자 온 거니?
Uncle Lu is downstairs.
루 삼촌은 아래에 있어요
Last night, Aunt Cai said
어제저녁에 야야 이모가
she would take the train
오늘 기차 타고
to go abroad for business today.
출국해서 사업을 하러 가신다고 하셨어요
My dad said he was off today.
오늘 마침 아빠가 쉬시는데
So he could send Aunt Cai off.
야야 이모가 세관을 통과하게 도와드린다네요
Yes, I did mention it.
맞아, 내가 말한 거야
Thank you so much.
고마워
You're welcome.
괜찮아요
Good morning.
좋은 아침이에요
Morning, Captain Lu.
좋은 아침입니다, 루 대장님
Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모
Son.
아들
What time did you sleep last night?
어제 몇 시에 잤어?
I didn't sleep.
안 잤어
When we are on duty,
임무를 나갈 때
it's normal not to sleep for a few days.
며칠 동안 침대에 눕지 못하는 건 정상이야
I'm used to it already.
익숙해졌어
It's not easy for the country to train you guys.
국가가 특수경찰을 양성하는 건 쉽지 않아
You should take care of your health.
몸을 아껴
So that you can work for a few more years.
그래야 몇 년 더 할 수 있지
It's the border.
국경선
Is the photo you sent to me
처음에 나한테 보낸 사진이
taken here?
여기야?
No.
아니
Later on,
이후에
if you come to Qining again,
네가 기회가 생겨 다시 치닝에 오면
I'll ask them to take you
내가 대원들에게 널 데리고 가서
to the place where the photo was taken.
사진에 찍힌 장소를 보여주라고 할게
I don't know
다음이
when will be the next time.
언제가 될지는 모르겠네
The view here is nice.
여기는 경치가 좋아
You should look more at
조국의 아름다운 강산을
the beautiful rivers and mountains of our motherland.
많이 봐야지
You've lived here for more than ten years.
넌 여기서 십여 년을 살았으니
I suppose
당연히
it feels like looking at your hometown.
고향 같겠네
[Qining Station]
[치닝역]
Captain Qin said
친 대장님이
he would help me watch over my car for a week
내가 돌아올 때까지 일주일 동안
until I returned.
차를 좀 봐주신다네
It's very nice of him.
좋은 분이시네
Captain Qin, thanks.
친 대장님, 감사합니다
Don't mention it. We're friends.
별말씀을요, 모두 친구잖습니까
Thank you.
감사해요
You may go through the customs and take the train from there.
저기에서 세관을 통과한 뒤 기차를 타면 됩니다
Captain Lu,
루 대장님
once again, I would like to express
다시 한번 대장님께
my sincere gratitude to you.
정말 감사드려요
I'll treat you to a meal when I get back to Beijing.
베이징에 돌아오시면 밥 살게요
Captain Lu, see you again.
루 대장님, 인연이 있으면 또 뵈어요
Bye.
안녕히 가세요
Okay, you can go now.
자, 그러면 너희는 가봐
Take care.
조심히 가
Have a safe trip.
가시는 길에 평안하길 바라요
Okay.
네
Bye.
가볼게
Aunt.
이모
Why don't you
왜
go abroad with them?
저분들과 함께 가지 않으시는 거예요?
I have work to do in Beijing.
이모는 아직 베이징에 일이 있어서
I need to go back to Beijing.
베이징으로 돌아가야 해
The three of them came to Qining
저 세분은 치닝에
for foreign trade.
대외 무역 사업 때문에 오셨죠
Aunt, why are you here?
이모는 여기 왜 왔어요?
Are you coming specially for Uncle Lu?
설마 옌천 삼촌 때문에 온 거에요?
No.
아니야
How could it be?
그렇지 않아
Xiaonan, if you keep talking nonsense,
샤오난, 자꾸 허튼소리를 하면
Aunt won't take you with her anymore.
이모가 널 안 데리고 가실 거야
Lu.
옌천
I've got an emergency mission.
긴급 임무야
I'll leave them to you.
두 사람은 네게 맡길게
Go ahead.
가봐
Xiaonan, be obedient to Aunt.
샤오난, 이모 말 잘 들어
Thank you.
감사합니다
Aunt, are you free after this?
이모, 이따가 별일 없으세요?
Yes, I am.
한가해
Can you help me pack up my luggage?
그러면 짐 싸는 것 좀 도와주실래요?
Why can't you do it yourself?
짐을 왜 혼자 못 싸는데?
What do you
다른 사람의 도움이
need help with from others?
필요한 물건이라도 있어?
None of us can.
남자는 믿을 수가 없어요
Men are not careful enough.
남자는 세심하지 못해서
We'll leave something out.
물건을 제대로 못 챙길 거예요
Okay.
알겠어
Thank you.
감사해요
Does he live alone?
샤오난은 평소에 혼자 살아?
When his dad comes,
친밍위가 돌아오면
he makes the bed up there
이층 침대 위층을 좀 치운 뒤에
and sleeps on the upper bunk.
위에서 지내
Why doesn't he apply for a dorm,
왜 기숙사를 신청하지 않아?
taking his son together?
샤오난이랑 함께 지내야지
In our profession,
우리 같은 직종은
once there is a mission,
해야 할 임무가 있을 때는
our working hours will be uncertain.
근무 시간이 일정하지 않아
If the kid stays in the dorm,
아이가 기숙사에서 사는 걸 꺼려
first, his resting will be disturbed.
왜냐면 휴식을 방해받을 수도 있고
Second, seeing his dad often goes out,
또 아버지가 자주 나가는 걸 보고
he'll be worried.
무턱대고 걱정할 것 같아서 그래
Kids nowadays are smart.
요즘 아이들은 모두 똑똑하잖아
He knows his dad's profession.
샤오난은 아빠가 무슨 일을 하는지 알고 있는데
He'll be worried anyway.
자연히 걱정할 수 밖에 없지
Besides,
그리고 지금
there're numerous movies about explosive ordnance disposal nowadays.
폭발물 제거하는 영화들이 많으니
Doesn't he
샤오난이 보고 나서
ask you guys after watching them?
궁금해하며 너희에게 묻지 않겠어?
Usually, we would say that
보통 우리는
the movie scenes are all made-up.
'영화는 다 지어낸 거야
It's not that dangerous.
그렇게 위험하지는 않아'라고 대답해
So it's all true.
원래는 모두 진짜고
It's dangerous, isn't it?
위험하지?
Can't you even tell your friends?
친구에게도 말할 수 없는 거야?
Every profession has difficulty.
모든 직업에는 고충이 있기 마련이지
There's nothing to say.
그래서 딱히 할 말은 없어
Is this all?
이게 다야?
Doesn't his father
아버지가
buy him clothes?
옷도 안 사주는 거야?
Also, why doesn't
그리고 집도
he rent
좀 더 큰 걸
a more spacious house?
빌리지 그랬어?
Isn't it too small
친 대장과 샤오난이 살기엔
for them to live here?
너무 작지 않아?
Are they your parents?
네 부모님이니?
It's Uncle Lu and...
옌천 삼촌이랑
Maybe
아마도 어쩌면
his alumnus.
삼촌의 동창이요
Why can't I understand
네 말을
what you said?
나는 왜 못 알아듣겠지?
Captain Lu is here.
루 대장이 왔으니
I have to say hello to him.
인사를 해야겠다
They're developing feelings for each other.
두 사람 지금 친해지는 중이에요
Are they helping you pack
두 사람이 네 짐을 챙기고
and move?
이사하는 걸 돕고 있구나
Thank you
그동안
for taking care of me all this time.
집주인 아저씨께서 보살펴 주셔서 감사했어요
Why did you close the door?
왜 문을 닫아?
The kid outside will get it wrong.
샤오난이 밖에서 문 닫는 거 보고 오해하겠다
We can talk conveniently if the door is closed.
문을 닫아야 얘기하기가 편해
His parents are divorced.
샤오난의 부모님은 이혼했어
Qin Mingyu got his son.
친밍위가 아이의 양육권을 가졌어
But deep down,
하지만 친밍위는 내심
he felt that he had dragged on Xiaonan's mother,
샤오난 엄마의 시간을 허비한 것 같아서
so he paid her a lot of money.
그녀에게 적지 않은 돈을 보냈지
I see.
그렇구나
Now he has to take care of his parents
친밍위는 지금 부모님을 부양하고
and raise his son.
아들도 키워야 해서
So he doesn't dare to spend money freely.
돈을 많이 쓸 수 없어
I've done packing the clothes.
옷은 내가 다 챙겼어
I'll leave the books for you to pack since you're more familiar with them.
책은 네가 잘 알고 있으니 네가 정리해
I'll go out first.
나 먼저 나갈게
♫We said it would last forever♫
♫ 우리 영원히 변치 말자고 했지만 ♫
♫But we were separated in the end♫
♫ 결국 헤어졌고 ♫
♫I wait until I give up all resistance♫
♫ 지금 흘러가는 시간을 버티며 ♫
♫Let time pass by♫
♫ 천천히 기다려왔지 ♫
♫Never thought that love♫
♫ 생각지도 못했어, 사랑이 ♫
♫Is not about the trials and tribulations♫
♫ 시련을 겪는 것처럼 ♫
My dad said...
아빠가…
My dad said that
아빠가 오늘 저녁에
he was not coming back for dinner tonight.
밥 먹으러 오지 않는대요
I got it.
알겠어
Let me see.
좀 보자
It's okay.
괜찮아, 괜찮아
I'll go out first.
나 먼저 나갈게
Otherwise, the kid will misunderstand.
그렇지 않으면 아이가 오해해
Get out.
나가
This is even more misunderstanding.
이러면 더 오해할 거야
Remember to take
잊지 말고
Qin Xiaonan's household registration permit
친샤오난의 호적부를 챙겨와
for boarding purposes.
비행기 탑승 때 필요해
Stay in the car.
이모랑 얘기 좀 하고 올 테니까
I need to talk to your aunt.
차 안에 있어
He doesn't have a household registration permit.
샤오난은 호적부가 없어
He doesn't?
없다고?
His household registration permit
샤오난의 호적은
has been with his mother.
줄곧 샤오난의 엄마한테 있어
After the divorce,
이혼 후에
his mother always hopes
샤오난의 엄마는 줄곧
Xiaonan can live with her.
샤오난이 그녀와 같이 살기를 원했어
Although the court has made a judgment,
법원에서 판결이 났지만
these two
이 두 사람은
have been dilly-dallying regarding household registration.
호적 변경을 계속 질질 끌고 있어
Qin Mingyu is also busy
친밍위도 바빠서
that he has no time to do it.
처리할 시간이 내내 없었어
Then, what should we do?
그러면 어떡하지?
Does he have a passport?
여권은 있어?
Yes.
응
Give me his passport first.
그러면 여권 먼저 줘
We'll discuss it after flying to Beijing.
베이징으로 간 다음에 다시 논의하자
But we need
하지만 학교에 다니려면
both the original and photocopy
호적 원본과
of his household registration permit.
사본이 필요해
The school will need to verify them.
학교에서 요구할 거야
We'll figure this out this month.
이번 달에 다시 방법을 생각해 보자
Poor kid.
아이가 참 안쓰럽네
[No self-heating food in hand-carry or check-in luggage is allowed]
[발열 식품 기내 반입 및 탁송 금지]
Passport.
여권 드려
I'll go back to Beijing after the Chinese New Year.
난 설 보내고 나서 베이징으로 가
It's almost time.
시간이 거의 다 됐네
You may go in.
들어가
Goodbye, Uncle Lu.
옌천 삼촌, 안녕히 계세요
Alright.
인사는 됐어
It's not like we'll never see each other again.
또 안 볼 사이도 아니잖아
We'll get going then.
그러면 우리 먼저 갈게
Why didn't your dad come to see you off?
너희 아버지는 왜 배웅하러 오지 않으셨어?
He hasn't been home for two days.
아빠는 요며칠 동안 집에 오지 않고
He only called once.
전화만 했었어요
It's okay.
괜찮아
You can visit him during the summer break.
여름 방학 때 아빠를 보러 돌아가면 되니까
I may not able to see him
돌아가도 아빠 얼굴을
even if I go back.
볼 수 있을지는 몰라요
Last year when I just arrived at Qining,
작년에 제가 막 치닝에 도착했을 때
my dad was on a mission,
아빠는 임무에 나가셨어요
a confidential one.
기밀 임무요
I couldn't see him for days.
몇 날 며칠 동안 아빠를 볼 수 없었어요
Then,
그러면
what about you?
넌 어떡해?
Was there no one who took care of you?
돌봐줄 사람이 없잖아
Yes.
있어요
The family of other team members took turns taking care of me.
대원들의 가족들이 번갈아 가며 저를 돌봐줬어요
But I cried every night.
그냥 매일 밤 울었어요
I thought my dad had abandoned me.
아빠가 날 버린 줄 알았거든요
Let me tell you.
이모가 말해줄 게 있어
I even cried
나는 고등학교 때도
when I was in high school.
울었어
My parents were divorcing at that time.
그때 우리 부모님이 이혼하셔서
So I cried a lot.
자주 울었지
You are so melodramatic.
이모, 애써 위로해주지 않아도 돼요
What's wrong with you?
너 어떻게 이럴 수 있어?
I was trying to comfort you.
널 위로해주려고 한 말이잖아
My dad said that I couldn't lie,
아빠가 거짓말하면 안 된다고 했어요
especially to you.
특히 이모에게는 더욱요
So I was being honest with you.
그래서 사실대로 얘기한 거예요
I won't argue with you.
너랑 따지고 들지 않을 거야
I'll take you hanging out tomorrow.
내일은 널 데리고 놀러 갈 건데
Where do you want to go?
가고 싶은 곳 있어?
The Palace Museum, the Temple of Heaven
고궁? 천단?
or the Great Wall?
아니면 만리장성?
How about this?
이렇게 하자
I'll take you
내가 널 데리고
to visit
먼저 유명한 곳부터
all the famous tourist spots
다 둘러보고
before we go to the local spots.
그다음에 조그마한 동네를 돌아보자
I don't want to go anywhere.
아무 데도 가고 싶지 않아요
We don't spend your dad's money.
네 아빠 돈을 쓰지 않을 거야
Your money is also money.
이모의 돈도 돈이에요
That's Xinhe Hospital.
저기는 신허 병원이네요
Do you know it?
저곳을 알아?
I know.
네
I used to go there when I was young.
어렸을 때 신허 병원에 자주 갔었어
And there's also a 341 Hospital.
341이라고 하나 더 있어
Is it nearby?
근처에 있는 거 아니에요?
I know it too.
거기도 알아요
You know a lot.
아는 게 많네
Uncle Lu told me.
옌천 삼촌이 말해줬어요
He said
삼촌이
he went to 341 Hospital
341에 가서
to visit a friend.
친구 한 명을 봤대요
A hospitalized friend.
입원해 있던 친구가
Is it you?
이모죠?
Maybe.
아마 그럴걸?
What do you mean by maybe?
아마 그럴 거라는 건 뭐예요?
I can't remember.
기억이 잘 안 난다는 거야
We are arriving at my home.
우리 집에 거의 다 왔어
That is the place you are going to stay
그곳이 네가 앞으로 한 달 동안
for the next month.
머물 곳이야
Come in.
들어가
This is the house I rent.
여기는 내가 빌린 집이야
You can look around later.
이따가 천천히 구경해
Come and change your shoes.
이리 와서 신발 갈아신어
Put them on.
신어, 이거 신으렴
I can't help you manage the suitcase today.
오늘 트렁크 정리를 할 수 없을 것 같아
Take out your pyjamas.
잠옷 한 벌 꺼내렴
I'll take you upstairs to take a shower and go to bed.
내가 위층으로 데려다줄 테니까 샤워하고 자
I usually
저는 평소에
sleep naked.
아무것도 안 입고 자요
You have to wear clothes here.
여기서는 옷을 입어야 해
I'm a girl.
나는 여자야
We should respect each other.
우리는 서로 존중해야 해
Okay.
알겠어요
I'm not familiar with this place.
저는 여기가 익숙하지 않으니
Can you buy it for me tomorrow?
내일 이모가 사주세요
Okay, leave it to me.
응, 내게 맡겨
[Hongrun Chenghua]
[훙룬청화]
Thanks.
고마워
You finally came back.
드디어 미련 없이 돌아왔네
Didn't you be tied
조국의 아름다운 강산에
by the beautiful mountains and rivers of our motherland?
붙잡히지 않았구나
Did anything happen
설 전인데 회사에
before the Chinese New Year?
별일 없었지?
No.
별일 없었어
It's almost New Year. Everyone is lazy.
곧 설이 다가오니까 모두 게을러졌어
That's good.
그러면 됐어
By the way,
맞다
there's a kid at my house.
우리 집에 지금
He's the child of my friend.
친구 아이가 와있어
So I won't work overtime.
그래서 야근은 안 해
If there are any needs,
무슨 일이 있으면
I'll work from home.
내가 집에 가져가서 할게
I'm fine with it.
난 괜찮아
I'm not the boss.
난 사장도 아니잖아
The boss is coming.
호랑이도 제 말 하면 온다더니
You're back.
다녀왔구나
Tomorrow is Laba.
내일이 납팔이네 (납팔 : 음력 12월 8일)
I was worried
이전에 네가
you wouldn't be able to catch up with the congee from Yonghe Palace.
옹화궁의 풍년 기원 죽을 먹지 못할까 걱정했었는데
Perfect.
마침 잘됐네
Oh yeah.
맞네요
I almost forgot.
사장님이 말하지 않으셨으면 잊을 뻔했어요
Are we going together tomorrow
그러면 내일 우리 같이 갈까
or I queue up for you first?
아니면 내가 먼저 가서 줄을 설까?
No need.
아니에요
I'll take someone there.
데리고 갈 사람이 있어요
Her friend's kid
구이샤오 친구네 애인데
will stay at her house until the Chinese New Year.
설 전까지 구이샤오 집에서 잠시 지낸다네요
Okay.
알았어
Qin Xiaonan.
친샤오난
-Qin... -Coming.
- 친… - 나가요
Slow down. Be careful not to fall.
천천히, 넘어지겠어
You've underestimated me.
저를 너무 얕잡아 보시네요
These stairs
이 계단은
won't hurt me.
저를 넘어뜨릴 수 없어요
Why didn't you turn on the lights?
왜 등을 안 켰어?
It was dark when I came in.
들어왔는데 어두워서
You scared me.
깜짝 놀랐잖아
I thought something happened to you.
무슨 일 생긴 줄 알았어
It's on.
켰어요
I've turned on the desk lamp.
책상 스탠드 켜놨어요
Your lights are too bright.
이 집의 등들은 너무 밝아요
It must consume a lot of electricity.
전력 낭비에요
I was not in the living room.
저는 거실에 있지 않으니
so I switched off all of them.
그래서 다 꺼놨어요
Come here.
이리 오렴
Women like shopping.
여자는 쇼핑을 좋아하죠
These are all for you.
이건 다 널 위해 산 거야
Heartless boy.
양심 없기는
I don't have that much money for you.
저는 이모에게 그렇게 많은 돈을 드리지 않았어요
They are at a 90% discount.
이건 모두 90% 할인하는
All are on sale.
특가 상품이야
I spent all the money
네가 준 돈을
you gave me to buy these.
모두 써서 이만큼 샀어
And I have points
그리고 난 포인트도 있어서
to redeem the gifts for free.
포인트로 샀지
Points?
포인트로
You can redeem so many things?
이렇게 많이 살 수 있다고요?
Of course.
응
I bought a lot in the past.
예전에 내가 많이 샀으니
So I got many points.
그러면 당연히 포인트가 많이 쌓였겠지
You lied to me.
거짓말
You money-grubber.
구두쇠야
You still have your wallet with you.
지갑을 몸에 지니고 있니
What do you want for dinner?
저녁 뭐 먹고 싶어?
I'll order takeout.
이모가 배달시킬게
[Qining City]
[치닝시]
You are leaving one week earlier
원래 계획보다
than planned.
일주일 일찍 떠나네
Are you anxious to return home?
집으로 돌아가고 싶은 마음이 굴뚝같나 보네
Your son is in Beijing.
네 아들이 베이징에 있는데
Aren't you worried?
걱정 안 하네
He is with Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 씨랑 있잖아
It's better than with you.
너랑 있는 것보다 마음이 놓여
Give this to Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 씨에게 줘
It's for Xiaonan's living expenses.
샤오난의 생활비야
Where did you get the money?
어디서 난 돈이야?
It's my bonus.
상여금이야
Gui Xiao bought not only clothes
구이샤오 씨가 샤오난에게
but also books for Xiaonan.
옷을 사주고 책도 사줬어
Right? She provides food and accommodation.
그렇지?  식사와 숙소를 제공해주는데
We can't pretend to be unaware of it.
우리가 모른 척할 수 없잖아
Also,
그리고
most importantly,
무엇보다 중요한 건
she introduced me to a school.
구이샤오 씨가 학교를 소개해 줬잖아
A school?
학교 말이야
This helped me a lot.
큰 도움을 받았고
She has done me a huge favour.
이건 하늘같이 큰 은혜야
Favour is the most valuable, do you know that?
은혜가 가장 값지다는 건 알아?
Take it.
받아
I will pay her.
내가 줄게
You should keep your bonus to celebrate the New Year with your family.
상여금은 설을 쇠는 데 써
What do you mean
내 아들인데
by paying for my son?
네가 돈을 주면 어떡해?
It's on your account.
일단 빌려줄게
When you become rich,
앞으로 네가 잘되면
pay me triple.
세 배로 갚아
Okay.
그래
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
I might come back in the future.
돌아올지도 몰라
You'd better not come back.
베이징에 가시니 돌아오지 않는 것이 좋습니다
It's not easy for you to transfer back there.
어렵게 베이징에 돌아가시는데
You should make up with
빨리 전 형수를
our ex-sister-in-law.
잡으셔야죠
You're over 30 years old
벌써 서른이 넘으셨는데
but you still care about your pride.
아직도 그렇게 체면을 차리십니까?
If you like her, just go for it.
그 사람이 좋으면 좋은 거지요
Shut up.
닥쳐
I'm leaving.
간다
Take a leave as soon as possible
빨리 휴가를 신청해서
and get the household registration permit back.
호적부 가지고 돌아와
I remember that.
기억하고 있어
[Beijing City]
[베이징시]
[Outside the Fifth Ring]
[5환 바깥 구역]
You're finally back.
드디어 돌아왔구나
Why didn't you inform me?
왜 나한테 말 안 했어?
I would pick you up.
내가 데리러 가려고 했는데
Let me see.
한번 보자
The campus beau in those days
당년의 킹카는
is still so handsome.
여전히 잘생겼네
Screw you!
닥쳐
Let's go.
가자, 가자
Go home.
집에 가자
I've booked
저녁에
the fanciest restaurant next to our house
네 환영회를 열려고 우리 집 옆에 있는
to welcome you.
가장 큰 식당을 예약했어
I don't have time to eat with you.
너랑 밥 먹을 시간이 없을 것 같다
My mum is sick.
엄마가 아프셔서
I came back
갈아입을 옷
to pack a change of clothes
몇 벌 챙겨서
before I go to the hospital.
병원에 가야 해
Your mum is sick?
아주머니께서 아프셔?
It's my fault.
내 잘못이야
I've been doing business
얼마 전까지
outside.
쭉 밖에서 장사하느라
So I haven't had a chance to visit your mum.
너희 집에 우리 엄마를 보러 가지 않았어, 난…
Meng Xiaoshan.
멍샤오산
Cancel the table
저녁에 예약한 그 자리를
I reserved for tonight.
취소해야 할 것 같아
I'm not going.
일이 생겨서 못 갈 것 같아
My younger brother
내 남동생이 여기에서
is dealing with the school application for Xiaonan.
샤오난의 학교 등록을 처리하고 있어
Have you got his household registration permit
호적부랑 출생증명서
and birth certificate?
받았어?
Don't worry.
걱정하지 마
I'll be there next time.
다음에 꼭 갈게
I haven't got them yet.
아직 못 받았어
Sorry, I'll be quick.
미안해, 최대한 빨리 받을게
Not yet.
아직도?
Let's make up for it later.
그러면 부족한 서류는 나중에 채우자
Since it's confirmed,
어쨌든 입학은 정해졌으니
I'll hold off for you with my guarantee.
내가 힘 좀 써서 우선 시간을 끌어볼게
Thanks.
고마워
What's wrong with you?
어떻게 된 거야?
How many donations
언니가 처음에
has Sister made for us
산간 지역에 보낼 성금을 얼마나 많이
for the mountainous area?
도와줬는데
Without her,
언니가 없었으면
would you have connected with so many prestigious schools?
네가 이렇게 좋은 학교를 알 수 있었겠어?
Guarantee?
힘 좀 쓴다고
Your guarantee is valid because of Sister.
그 힘은 다 언니가 준 거 아냐?
Yes.
그렇지
Don't bother him, Sister.
얘와 상대하지 말아요, 언니
Well,
그게
as for the procedures afterwards,
이후에 또 어떤 수속을 밟아야 하는지
make a list for me.
목록을 만들어서 내게 주면
I'll finish them during the winter break.
겨울 방학 내에 처리할게
I'll give it to you tomorrow.
내일 줄게
Okay.
응
I'll get it for you, Uncle.
제가 치울게요, 삼촌
Good boy.
정말 착하네
You've been to the north
북쪽에 가서 기분 전환을 한다더니
for less than a week,
일주일도 안 돼서
but you took back
일면식도 없는
a kid you didn't know before.
아이를 데려왔네
Not only are you
학교 입학 문제를
helping with his education,
해결하는 건 그렇다 치고
but you also filled in his regular address as your home.
아이가 상주하는 주소를 자기 집으로 기재하다니
Sister, if you weren't a woman
누나, 누나가 여자가 아니고
and couldn't satisfy the condition,
우리 능력이 충분하지 않았다면
I would have thought that
나는 정말 이 아이가
he was
누나가 밖에서 몰래 낳은
your illegitimate child.
사생아인 줄 알았을 거야
You're right.
아이와 언니가 정말 닮았다고는 하지 마
Right?
그렇지?
Let's have dinner together tonight.
저녁같이 먹자
I'll book a restaurant.
식당 예약할게
Don't bother, Sister. You're always so generous.
그러지 마, 누나, 매번 누나 돈을 쓰게 하네
Can't I take the kid
아이와 함께 고기를 먹고 싶은데
to have some meat?
안 돼?
Go. Put on your down jacket.
가서 패딩 입고 와
The one I bought for you.
내가 저번에 사준 그 옷 말이야
How about this?
그러면 이렇게 하자
We'll go downstairs and wait in the car.
우리는 먼저 출발할게
Okay, see you downstairs.
응, 밑에서 보자
Take it.
들고 있어
Okay, let's go.
됐다, 가자
[Inpatient Building]
[입원동]
Here's your bill.
명세서 받으세요
Okay.
네
Do you have enough money? I have some with me.
충분해? 나 돈 있어
Yes.
충분해
It's settled.
해결했어
It's not like you to smile at your phone.
핸드폰을 보고 웃는 건 너 같지 않은데
Is it a beauty from Qining?
치닝의 미녀야?
Watch over my mum.
우리 엄마 좀 봐줘
I'll pay the bill.
가서 수납할게
My dad said
아빠가 그랬어요
Uncle Lu always risked his life on missions.
옌천 삼촌은 임무를 나가서 사력을 다해
He led the team to arrest the culprits
대대를 이끌고 사람을 잡았대요
for two days and two nights.
이틀 밤낮으로
After crossing five snow-capped mountains,
설산 다섯 개를 넘고
the claws of police dogs covered with blood,
경찰견의 발톱은 온통 피투성이인 채
he was still chasing after them.
계속 쫓았대요
In the end, he caught them.
나중에는 따라잡았대?
Nobody can get away
옌천 삼촌은
from Uncle Lu.
못 잡는 사람이 없어요
Once, they went on a mission
또 다른 임무에서는
at a forbidden zone of life
해발 5,000여 미터쯤에 있는
with an elevation of about 5,000 metres.
황무지에 갔어요
They'd walked a dozen kilometres
십여 km를
and carried out the villagers who passed out with oxygen deficiency.
저산소증으로 혼수상태에 빠진 치닝 사람을 업고 걸었어요
The villagers recovered after being carried out,
돌아온 후에 치닝 사람은 괜찮았는데
but some team members had altitude sickness
고산병 증상이 나타난 대원은
and almost died.
하마터면 죽을 뻔했어요
Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모
How did you
옌천 삼촌과는
know each other?
어떻게 알게 된 사이에요?
We're alumni.
동창이야
You're indeed alumni?
정말 동창이에요?
I thought it was an excuse.
핑계인 줄 알았어요
His name was Lu Chen at first.
루옌천의 원래 이름은 '루천'이고
Later, he changed his name by adding Yan in the middle.
나중에 이름을 바꾸면서 '옌'을 추가한 거야
Do you know that?
알고 있었니?
No wonder.
어쩐지…
No wonder what?
어쩐지?
That day in the parking lot,
그날 주차장에서
you called him Lu Chen.
삼촌을 루천이라 부르기에
I felt weird at that time.
좀 이상했어요
Although we went to the same school,
우리는 같은 학교였지
I hadn't met him
그런데 처음에는
at first,
나도 루옌천을 본 적이 없었어
but always heard about
늘
Lu Chen in the 12th grade
루천이라는 삼 학년 학생이
having a good look.
엄청 잘생겼다고 듣기만 했었지
And then?
그 뒤에는요?
That's our business. Kids can't inquire about it.
어른의 일을 캐묻지 말렴
[Year 2020]
[2020년]
[Spring 2008]
[2008년 봄]
Xiao.
구이샤오
This is my cousin, Lu Chen.
우리 사촌 오빠 '루천'이야
Lu Yanchen.
루옌천
Yes, when he was in school,
맞다, 나중에 학교 갈 때
he changed his name because it duplicated with others.
이름을 바꿨어
But we still
하지만 가족들은
call him Lu Chen.
모두 루천이라고 불러
Boss, two more.
사장님, 꼬치 두 개만 더 주세요
Okay.
알겠습니다
Hi, Gui Xiao.
구이샤오, 왔어?
Have you done your summer homework?
여름방학 숙제를 다 했나 보네?
Yet you're hanging out here.
뛰쳐나와 놀기는
Aren't you the same?
너도 그렇잖아?
I'm going to celebrate Meng Xiaoshan and others' graduation.
오늘은 멍샤오산 졸업을 축하하러 가는 거잖아
It's an exceptional case.
특수 상황이지
Are you coming to celebrate Meng Xiaoshan's birthday,
갓 졸업한 그 멍샤오산의
who has just graduated?
생일 축하하러 왔지?
Yes.
네
Turn right. The innermost one.
오른쪽으로 돌은 뒤 제일 안쪽에 있는 방이다
Thank you.
감사해요
What are you laughing at?
왜 웃어?
Believe it or not, I'll pocket all in the next round.
믿거나 말거나, 다음 샷에 다 넣을 거야
I don't think so.
그럴 것 같진 않네
We have made a bet.
우리 내기하고 있어
Whoever wins will buy the beverages.
이긴 사람이 마실 걸 사기로 했어
Won't he get a heat stroke
저렇게 껴입었는데
wearing so much?
더위 안 먹나?
Chen.
천 형
Chen, this is Meng Xiaoshan's sister
여긴 멍샤오산의 여동생이고
and my sister-in-law, Gui Xiao.
내 처제, 구이샤오에요
Game.
게임 끝
Let me play in the next game.
다음 판은 내가 할래
You're even shorter than the cue stick.
넌 아직 당구봉보다 작으니까
You'd better just watch them playing.
얌전히 구경해
Didn't you make a block booking?
여기를 빌렸잖아?
There are no outsiders here. I'm just playing for fun.
다른 사람도 없으니까 이번 판은 내가 칠래
Yes.
맞아
You've booked for a whole afternoon anyway.
어차피 오후 내내 빌렸으니까
Just let her play.
그냥 치게 해 줘
I'll go get some water.
물 좀 가져올게
Brother, where are you going?
형, 어디 가?
I'll play with you for one game.
내가 같이 쳐줄게
You've been sitting here all afternoon.
오후 내내 앉아 있더니
You finally have the mood to exercise.
드디어 움직일 마음이 생긴 거예요?
I am no match for you.
나는 그쪽을 이길 수 없는 걸요
I'll use my left hand.
왼손으로 할게
The rule is who clears the table first, who wins.
공을 다 넣는 사람이 이기는 거야
In this way, the chances of winning are high.
이렇게 얘기하니까 제가 이길 확률이 엄청 크군요
I'll start the move.
제가 시작할게요
Of course.
당연하지
♫Hi, what day is today?♫
♫ 하이, 오늘은 무슨 요일이니 ♫
Chen has given in so much.
천 오빠가 이렇게까지 해주는데
How can he not let you start the move?
시구를 못 하게 하겠어?
♫Can I see you?♫
♫ 널 만날 수 있니 ♫
♫Let my heartbeat continue at 110 bpm♫
♫ 심장 박동이 계속 110이 되도록 ♫
♫Bang bang bang So annoying♫
♫ 가슴은 쿵쾅거리네 ♫
♫Oh, you're not up yet♫
♫ 오, 넌 아직 일어나지 않았고 ♫
♫You didn't see my message♫
♫ 내가 보낸 메시지를 보지 못했어 ♫
♫Did anyone tell you♫
♫ 누군가 네게 알려주지 않았니 ♫
♫I miss you so much♫
♫ 내가 네 생각을 많이 한다는 걸 ♫
♫Love is in fashion♫
♫ 연애가 유행이라지만 ♫
♫But you want to be quiet♫
♫ 넌 그러지 않았으면 좋겠어 ♫
♫Even the moon is awakened♫
♫ 달이 깨어나면 ♫
♫Even the meteor stops♫
♫ 별똥별은 멎겠지 ♫
♫Love songs are popular♫
♫ 사랑의 노래가 유행하고 있어 ♫
♫I'll sing for you♫
♫ 네게 노래를 불러줄게 ♫
♫We'll take our time to develop our relationship♫
♫ 우리는 천천히 감정을 키워가자 ♫
♫I believe you can do it♫
♫ 네가 할 수 있음을 믿어 ♫
No way, Chen.
아니, 천 오빠
♫Hi, what day is today?♫
♫ 하이, 오늘은 무슨 요일이니 ♫
Don't bully
우리 구이샤오를
Gui Xiao.
이렇게 괴롭히지 마세요
Yes.
맞아요
♫Can I see you?♫
♫ 널 만날 수 있니 ♫
Today is Meng Xiaoshan's birthday.
오늘 멍샤오산 생일인데
Why are you bullying her sister?
멍샤오산 동생을 괴롭혀서 뭐 해요?
♫Let my heartbeat continue at 110 bpm♫
♫ 심장 박동이 계속 110이 되도록 ♫
Yeah, Chen.
그러니까요, 천 형
Give in to her.
하나는 양보해줘요
♫Bang bang bang So annoying♫
♫ 가슴은 쿵쾅거리네 ♫
He's already using his left hand.
왼손으로 치는데도 양보하라고
Why don't you ask Gui Xiao
차라리 구이샤오가
to grab the balls and put them directly in the pockets?
당구봉으로 치는 거 말고 손으로 집어서 공을 넣게 하지 그래
♫Oh, you're not up yet♫
♫ 오, 넌 아직 일어나지 않았고 ♫
♫You didn't see my message♫
♫ 내가 보낸 메시지를 보지 못했어 ♫
Do you want me to take a dive?
양보해줄까?
♫Did anyone tell you?♫
♫ 누군가 네게 알려주지 않았니 ♫
No.
필요 없어요
♫I miss you so much♫
♫ 내가 네 생각을 많이 한다는 걸 ♫
♫Love is in fashion♫
♫ 연애가 유행이라지만 ♫
♫But you want to be quiet♫
♫ 넌 그러지 않았으면 좋겠어 ♫
♫Even the moon is awakened♫
♫ 달이 깨어나면 ♫
♫Even the meteor stops♫
♫ 별똥별은 멎겠지 ♫
♫Love songs are popular♫
♫ 사랑의 노래가 유행하고 있어 ♫
♫I'll sing for you♫
♫ 네게 노래를 불러줄게 ♫
I'll go and buy something.
뭐 좀 사 올게
♫We'll take our time to develop our relationship♫
♫ 우리는 천천히 감정을 키워가자 ♫
♫I believe you can do it♫
♫ 네가 할 수 있음을 믿어 ♫
♫Love is in fashion♫
♫ 연애가 유행이라지만 ♫
♫But you want to be quiet♫
♫ 넌 그러지 않았으면 좋겠어 ♫
♫Even the moon is awakened♫
♫ 달이 깨어나면 ♫
♫Even the meteor stops♫
♫ 별똥별은 멎겠지 ♫
♫Love songs are popular♫
♫ 사랑의 노래가 유행하고 있어 ♫
It's hot.
뜨거워 죽겠네
♫I'll sing for you♫
♫ 네게 노래를 불러줄게 ♫
I forgot to park it in the shade.
그늘에 주차하는 걸 까먹었네
♫We'll take our time to develop our relationship♫
♫ 우리는 천천히 감정을 키워가자 ♫
Did you burn your butt?
엉덩이 데었네
♫I believe you can do it♫
♫ 네가 할 수 있음을 믿어 ♫
Chen.
천 형
Chen, are you leaving?
천 형, 가요?
Later I found out
나중에서야 알았다
something happened to Lu Chen's family
그해 수능 전날
[Summer 2008]
[2008년 여름]
one day before the Gaokao.
루천의 집에 큰일이 생겨서
He didn't settle it until the next afternoon
다음 날 오후가 되어서야 해결이 되었고
and missed
오전 첫 시험을
the first exam in the morning.
놓쳤다는 걸
No one knew
그가
whether he was going to repeat his final year
도대체 재수했는지
or work at the repair factory of his family.
아니면 집에서 운영하는 카센터에 갔는지 아무도 모른다
Since then,
그 이후로
I never saw him again.
난 다시는 그를 본 적이 없었다
Until...
그때까지…
Sister-in-law, here.
처제, 이리 와
I'll treat you to pancakes.
오빠가 젠빙 사줄게
Take it easy.
조심해
Here, the pancake is ready.
자, 젠빙이 다 됐습니다
Look how skinny my sister-in-law is.
우리 처제가 얼마나 말랐는지 좀 보세요
Add two eggs for me. Pick the big ones.
계란 두 개, 큰 걸로 넣어주세요
Okay.
알겠습니다
Boss, a pancake, please.
사장님, 젠빙 하나 주세요
Okay, please wait a moment.
알겠습니다, 조금만 기다려주세요
Come on, handsome, your pancakes.
자, 잘생긴 오빠, 젠빙 받아요
Here.
자, 받아
Thank you.
고마워
You're welcome.
예의를 차리고 그래
My future bridesmaid.
미래의 신부 들러리님
My bike.
자전거 주세요
My brother didn't take the Gaokao that day
우리 오빠는 그날 수능을 안 봤어
because he applied for the police academy
오빠가 이모부 몰래
without telling his dad.
몰래 경찰학교에 지원했거든
His dad made a scene before the exam
시험 전에 한바탕 난리 치고
and locked him up in the garage
이모부는 오빠를 자동차 수리소에
for two days and three nights.
꼬박 이틀 밤을 가두었어
The first exam was finished by then.
첫 번째 과목 시험이 끝날 때가 되어서야
He was released in secret
둘째 이모가
by my aunt after that.
몰래 오빠를 풀어 줬어
But it was too late.
하지만 결국 늦었지
Why?
왜?
Even he applied for the police academy, so what?
경찰학교가 어때서?
My aunt had divorced my uncle before.
우리 둘째 이모랑 이모부는 이혼한 적이 있어
She married a cop after that.
이모가 재혼한 상대는 경찰이었지
That cop was very nice.
그 경찰은 정말 훌륭했어
He treated my cousins well.
우리 사촌 오빠랑 사촌 언니한테 너무 잘해줬는데
But later he got sick and died.
후에 병으로 돌아가셨어
My aunt had no income.
우리 둘째 이모는 수입이 없으니
She couldn't afford to raise two children.
두 아이를 키울 수 없어서
So she remarried my uncle.
이모부와 또 재혼하셨지
Probably because of jealousy.
질투때문인 것 같아
I heard it from my mum.
엄마가 하는 말을 들어보니
When my uncle
우리 이모부는
knew my cousin had applied for the police academy,
루천 오빠가 경찰학교에 지원한 걸 알고
he went crazy.
미친 사람처럼 행동하셨어
He must have recalled
아마도
my aunt's second marriage.
둘째 이모가 재혼했던 일이 생각났을 거야
You can never ask
이 말은 절대로
my cousin about this.
우리 사촌 오빠한테 묻지 마
We don't talk much.
나는 네 사촌 오빠랑 얘기를 잘 하지 않아
Really?
그래?
I thought you were close
멍샤오산 때문에
because of Meng Xiaoshan.
둘이 잘 아는 사이인 줄 알았어
Gui Xiao. I'll wait for you at the school gate.
구이샤오, 학교 문 앞에서 기다릴게
It's my brother's birthday today.
오늘 우리 형 생일이야
Do I need to buy a gift?
그러면 선물을 사야 할까?
Come on.
됐거든
You bought plush toys
우리 반의 어떤 친구가 생일이면
for every student in our class on their birthdays.
너는 생일 선물로 인형을 사주잖아
You've almost
그 명품점이
hollowed out the shop.
네게 다 털릴 지경이야
Meng asked you to go empty-handed.
샤오산 누나가 빈손으로 오래
Okay. Wait for me.
알았어, 그러면 기다려
I'll hand in the paper.
답안지 제출하러 간다
He must be there on Haidong's birthday.
하이둥의 생일이니 루천은 반드시 있을 거야
[Lu Zheng Automobile Repair]
[루정 카센터]
This is the factory of Chen's family.
여기가 바로 천 형네 공장이야
But customers usually don't come here.
근데 손님들은 보통 여기로 오지 않고
They have to go to the storefront if they need the repairs.
수리를 맡기려고 매장으로 가
Chen.
천 형
You're here.
왔어?
Sit here.
여기 앉아
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Let me introduce them.
소개할게
These are my old classmates.
이 사람들은 모두 내 동창들이고
This is Meng Xiaoshan's sister.
여기는 멍샤오산의 동생
Her name is Gui Xiao.
구이샤오야
This is my younger brother, Hai Jianfeng.
여기는 내 동생, 하이젠펑
They are our own people.
모두 친한 사이야
Lu Chen's room is too cold.
루천 방은 너무 추워
Put it on.
입고 있어
You guys are still in high school.
몇 명은 아직 고등학교에 다니고 있으니까
You can't drink.
술 마시면 안 돼
Don't worry. I won't let them drink.
걱정하지 마, 못 마시게 할게
This should be where he lives.
여기는 그가 사는 곳일 거야
Is this
혹시
Hai Jianfeng's best friend?
하이젠펑이랑 엄청 친한 친구 아냐?
No, no.
아니, 아니
No.
아니에요
This is my sister.
누나나 다름없어요
He's no match for Gui Xiao.
이 자식은 우리 구이샤오만 못해
I'm serious.
진심이야
My sister not only has good grades
내 여동생은 성적이 우수하고
but also is talented in sports
또 체육 특기생에
and is a member of the school choir.
학교 합창단이야
She is definitely
단연코
the favourite of all teachers.
각 과목 선생님의 둘도 없는 보물이지
A straight-A student? Not bad.
공붓벌레네, 대단한데
Are there enough dishes?
음식은 충분해?
No.
아니
I want to eat pickled cabbage with vinegar sauce.
이 추류바이차이를 더 먹고 싶은데
One more.
한 그릇 더 줘
Coming.
왔다
Good.
좋았어
Try it.
먹어 봐
Chen.
천 형
Your cooking is so good.
솜씨가 정말 대단하네요
Of course.
당연하지
You don't have to rush back, right?
천천히 집에 돌아가
It's my birthday today.
오늘 생일인데
We finally get together.
모처럼 다 같이 모였잖아
Otherwise,
아니라면
I don't dare to waste your study time.
감히 네가 공부해야 하는 시간을 허비했겠어
No hurry.
급하지 않아
It's Friday.
오늘 금요일이잖아
Okay, that's good.
그래, 그럼 됐어
Try it. Lu Chen is good at cooking.
루천의 솜씨를 맛보자